[MUSIC]
[음악]
We talked about accuracy and errors that a classifier might make.
분류기의 정확도와 오류를 알아봤습니다
But there are different kinds of errors.
오류에도 여러 유형이 있습니다
So this kind of errors are called types of mistakes.
이런 오류는 실수 유형라고 합니다
It's important to look at the types of mistakes a classifier might make.
분류기가 실수하는 유형을 살피는 건 중요합니다
And one way to do that is through what's called a confusion matrix.
한 가지 방법은 혼동 행렬이라는 도구를 통하는 것입니다
So, let's take that in a little bit.
잠시 살펴보죠
So we're talking about the relationship between the true label and
참 라벨과 예측 라벨의 관계를
whatever classifier predicts, so the predicted label.
나타냅니다
So let's say that if the true label is positive, and we predict a positive value
참 라벨이 긍정이고 그 문장에 대해 긍정적이라고
for that sentence, we call that a true positive because we got it right.
예측했다면 옳으니 참 긍정이라고 합니다
Similarly if the true label is negative and
비슷하게 참 라벨이 부정인데
we predict that negative we call that a true negative.
예측도 부정이라면 참 부정이라고 부릅니다
That's good cuz we got that right.
맞췄으니 좋은 일이죠
Now, there is two kinds of mistakes that I can make.
실수도 두 종류가 있습니다
So, for example, if the true label's positive, but
참 라벨이 긍정인데 예측이 부정이면
we predicted as negative, we call that a false negative.
거짓 부정이라고 부릅니다
We said it was negative, but that was false cuz it's positive.
부정이라고 했는데 긍정이니 거짓입니다
Similarly, if the true label is negative when we predicted as positive,
비슷하게 참 라벨이 부정인데 긍정으로 예측했으면
we call that a false positive.
거짓 긍정이라고 부릅니다
It was negative, but we predicted it as positive.
부정이었지만 긍정으로 예측했습니다
And false positives and false negatives can have different impacts
거짓 긍정과 거짓 부정은 실무에서
on what can happen in practice with your classifier.
다른 영향력을 가집니다
So let's look at a couple practical examples of that.
몇 가지 예를 들어봅시다
So let's look at two applications, and
두 영역을 보고 거짓 긍정과 거짓 부정의
what the cost has of false positives versus false negatives.
비용을 알아봅시다
So, if you consider spam filtering, a false negative is
스팸 필터링이 대상일 때 거짓 부정은
an email that was spam but went into my folder it thought it was not spam.
스팸 이메일인데 아니라고 판단한 겁니다
So that's just annoying I got another spam email in my inbox.
이건 짜증이 좀 나는 정도죠
Maybe it's bad but not super bad.
나쁘지만 아주 나쁘지는 않습니다
However, if you look at a false positive
거짓 긍정이 되면
that's an email that was not spam that got labeled as spam, went to my spam filter.
스팸이 아닌 이메일이 스팸 폴더로 가버린 것이죠
I never saw it, I lost that email forever.
그 이메일을 못 보게 되고 결국 유실됩니다
That has a higher cost.
비용이 높죠
Now we can also look at medical diagnosis or
두 번째로 의료진단과 다른 영역을
other applications as a second application.
살펴보죠
So what's a false negative in medical diagnosis?
외료진단에서 거짓 부정은 뭐죠?
False negative is, there's a disease that I have but
거짓 부정은 질병에 걸렸는데
it didn't get detected, so the classifier said it was negative.
검출이 안 된거고, 분류기가 부정이라 판단한 것이죠
They don't have the disease.
병이 없다고요
So in this case, the disease goes untreated,
이 경우 질병은 검출되지 않는 것인데
which can be a really bad thing.
아주 나쁜 겁니다
But the false positives can also be a bad thing.
하지만 거짓 긍정도 나쁩니다
That is, I classify as having the disease when I never had the disease.
분류기가 질병이 있다고 판단했는데 사실 없는 것이죠
In this case I get treated potentially with a really bad drug or
이 경우 부작용이 심한 독한 약을
false side effect for diseases that I never had.
있지도 않은 질병에 쓰게 되죠
So it's a little bit unclear what's worse, having a false positive or
거짓 긍정과 거짓 부정 중
a false negative.
어떤 게 더 나쁜지는 불확실합니다
In medialc complications it really depends on the cost of the treatment and
의학 영역에서는 치료 비용, 부작용과
how many side effects it had versus how bad the disease can be.
질병의 심각성 등에 달려 있습니다
Now this relationship between the true label and the predicted label,
참 라벨과 예측 라벨,
false positive, false negatives, is called the Confusion Matrix.
거짓 긍정과 거짓 부정 사이의 관련성을 혼동 행렬이라 부릅니다
This matrix we just do.
방금 했던 것이죠
So for example, let's say that we have a setting with a 100 test examples.
100 테스트 예제를 가진 설정이 있다고 합시다
And we have of those, 60 positive and 40 are negative.
그 중 60이 긍정, 40이 부정입니다
So there's a little bit of class imbalance but not too much.
클래스 불균형이 조금 있지만 많지는 않지요
So of those 60 true positives, if I say I got 50 of them correct,
60개의 참 긍정 중에 50개를 맞추고
well of the 42 negatives
40개의 참 부정 중에
I got 35 of them correct.
35개를 맞춥니다
Let's see what we've learned.
배운 걸 되짚어 보죠
So out of the 100 examples I got 85 correct.
100개의 예제 중에 85개를 맞췄습니다
So we can talk about our accuracy.
정확도를 논할 수 있겠죠
Accuracy is 85 correct over 100, which is 0.85.
100개 중에 85를 맞췄으니 0.85입니다
And we can also discuss the true positives and the true negatives.
참 긍정과 참 부정에 대해서도 다뤄보죠
Sorry, the false positives and the false negatives, so of the positives,
죄송합니다. 거짓 긍정과 거짓 부정에서
I got labeled as negative, that's a false negative.
긍정인데 부정이란 라벨이 붙은 게 거짓 부정입니다
And that was ten, I had ten false negatives and on the other hand,
거짓 부정이 10개가 있고
of the true negatives we get five false positive.
거짓 긍정이 5개가 있습니다
So in this example, we got 85% accuracy.
이 예제에서 85% 정확도를 냈습니다
We got a higher false negative rate, than we had a false positive rate.
거짓 부정율이 거짓 긍정율보다 더 높습니다
Now those words, false positive,
거짓 긍정, 거짓 부정은 클래스가
false negative, apply only for minor classification for two classes.
두 개일때만 가능한 분류입니다
But the ideal confusion matrix works well even when you have more classes.
혼동 행렬은 클래스가 더 많아도 잘 작동하죠
So let's talk about a simple example of that.
간단한 예를 봅시다
So let's say that I have 100 test examples and this is for
의료진단 100 테스트 예제에서
medical diagnosis, so there's 3 classes, healthy, cold or flu.
건강, 감기, 독감으로 클래스 3개가 있습니다
And of the 100 test subjects we had 70 with that were healthy,
100명의 조사 대상에서 70명은 건강했고
20 that had cold, and 10 that had the flu.
20명은 감기고 10명은 독감입니다
And let's suppose that we got 60 correct for
건강한 사람들에서 60명을 맞췄고
healthy, we got 12 correct for cold,
감기 걸린 사람들 중 12명을 맞췄고
and we got 60, 12, 8 correct for flu.
독감 걸린 사람들 중 8명을 맞췄다고 합시다
So, the total, our accuracy, here,
그러면 전체 정확도는 80인데
was 80, which is 60 plus 12 plus 8 divided by 100.
60 + 12 + 8 나누기 100에서 나온 수치죠
So that 0.8, 80% accuracy.
0.8 80% 정확도입니다
But we can talk about the false predictions.
거짓 예측에 대해서도 알아보죠
So from healthy there were ten mistakes.
건강한 사람들에게 10개의 실수가 있었습니다
And we can say it's more common to confuse healthy with having a cold
건강한 사람에게 감기가 있다고 혼동하는 게
than it is with having the flu, because the flu is a more complex disease so
독감이 있다는 것보다 흔한데
we might have those ten mistakes.
독감이 복합질환이라 10개의 실수 중
Eight were confused with code and two were confused with flu.
8개가 감기고 2개가 독감입니다
Cold can go both ways.
감기는 양방향으로 갈 수 있습니다
So we made eight mistakes.
실수가 8개였습니다
Maybe you can say half of them got confused with healthy and
절반은 건강과 혼동했고 절반은
half of them got diagnosis something stronger the flu.
독감으로 진단됐습니다
Well of the two mistakes for the flu, then maybe we say that we
독감으로 진단된 2개의 실수 중
made no mistakes often, nobody that came in for flu was thought oh you're healthy.
건강하다고 판별된 사람은 없는데 독감 걸려서 온 사람 보고 건강하다고 하지는 않기 때문이죠
But two of those ten were thought to have just a cold and not the flu.
10개 중 2개는 감기로 판단된 사례입니다
So this is an example of a confusion matrix, we can really
혼동 행렬 예제였는데 어떤 종류의 실수를
understand the types of mistakes we made and we can interpret those.
했고 어떻게 해석하는지 배울 수 있습니다
And this is a really important thing to do in classification
분류에서는 아주 중요한 일이죠